Agent is actually a wrapper around your
LLM. So, imagine you are starting your
session and asking Claude code to
develop something and all of this
information goes into the context and
every time Claude code tries to fix the
bug, it actually sends this information
to the context window. So, all these
trace logs, trace backs, all this goes
into the context. We are in the era
where we can just populate in plain
language a huge document describing how
something complex should work and agent
will come up with a roughly working
solution on its own. Usually, it won't
be exactly what you want and you will
need to anyway like manual interventions
and fixes to validate that. But again,
it's not a bug, it's a feature because
we are underspecifying stuff. What's a
good way to be able to eval an agent's
capability as let's say code generation?
>> So, it's a huge topic.
[Music]
Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So, whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast for you. A
really quick ask, 90% of people who are
listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So, if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. All
right, back to the episode. Hello and
welcome to another episode of the AI and
Native Dev. I'm super excited about this
episode. We're going to go uh we're
actually going to talk about uh agents
and we're going to do a kind of like a
little 101 uh with agents. I know there
are a ton of people who have absolutely
gone deep with agents, tried every
single agents. But actually, do you know
what? There are a huge number of
developers as we found out at various
conferences recently that when we talk
about agents, we actually need to do
more content which is more about 101.
Let's talk about why agents are useful,
what are the constituent parts of
agents, how can we best use them, what
are they good for, what are they not,
and also what is the difference between
agents and other types of AI uh
you know pieces like a
like an assistant or perhaps a bot or
something like that. Joining me today uh
is is Max Shaposhnikov uh who is going
to be talking uh about all of these
wonderful agent 101s. Uh Max is a
research engineer at uh Tessel. Max,
welcome to the podcast. How are you? Hi,
thank you very much for this great
introduction. Yeah, I'm happy to be
there and happy to talk about agents 101
and share some some insights, some
details about that. So, yeah, let's dive
in. And this is the kind of thing Max is
a Max is uh a very humble but very very
smart uh person. So, while we're going
to try and fit this into an episode,
this may be a part one of seven or
eight. We will see. Uh but but Max, what
do we actually what Max, will you tell
us a little bit about yourself first? Um
what you've been working on, what your
passions are in the in the AI space.
It's my first experience like working
with code gen uh here at Tessel. Um I
work as a research engineer as I
mentioned. Our focus here on like making
agents reliable and be able to produce
uh robust code such that whenever your
agent develop you something, you can be
confident and sure that it develop
something good, something which you can
trust and you don't need to, you know,
expend hours verifying the results. So,
that's the thing which we're building
here at Tessel. Um beyond that, my
previous experience was a lot uh about
pre-training of the LLMs.
I worked at a big tech and uh again like
I was in the pre-training team in the
foundational LLM team where we focused
on
figuring out how to how to train
large-scale models uh that could be
later fine-tuned for specific tasks uh
and again like coding is one such task.
I didn't uh work with that before
Tessel.
Uh my specification was like natural
language processing, text-to-speech, and
other more common multimodalities.
Interesting, very cool. And and I think,
you know, when we think about think
about agents, there's a bunch that's
kind of, you know, similar across
irrespective of what the agent's trying
to do or what it's trying to whether
it's trying to generate code or not. And
let's kind of first of all position an
agent with other AI entities. So, I
mentioned at the start, you know, we
have assistants and that's really where
when we think about AI code generation,
typically the the early stage co-pilots
of of the year were very much assistants
to us. What makes the difference between
an agent, an assistant, and a and even a
bot? I think um
the right answer would be like uh
there are like
couple of these types of entities as I
mentioned and uh actually never thought
about that co-pilot thing, but I think
it's a fourth uh such modality. So, in
my picture, there are like bots,
co-pilots, AI assistants, and AI agents.
So, that's like a more complete picture.
Uh I would say like the bots is the the
oldest type of these um
uh you know, in this space. Uh usually,
they are automating super simple
scripted tasks.
Uh they don't include
uh multi-turn conversations. They are
having like a predetermined dialogue
tree like or dialogue flow and you know
and you can forecast and understand like
in advance in which position, in which
node the the bot will be.
Um so, you script all the logic. In some
specific cases, there might might be
like ML models applied, but again like
they are super simple like
classification tasks, named entity
recognition. That's it. And we're
talking about typical bots, website bots
that we love to hate. Yeah, yeah, I get
you. Yeah. At some point like I think in
that that trend about building bots
started since uh Alexa, maybe like 2015,
right? Like when first version of Alexa
was released and Siri was released. So,
there was like a lot of hope that bots
will be the future.
Uh well, uh apparently, we're still not
there.
Uh bots are still not able to do lots
of, you know, cool stuff. Uh again like
they are super simple in the nature in
their nature. They are prescriptive.
They have like specific patterns about
how how to perform specific tasks and
they are very limited. They don't have
an environment and environment is a very
key like important word which we'll talk
later. Um
so, moving next, I think that the next
in this uh hierarchy is the co-pilots.
Uh co-pilots are like auto-complete.
Uh usually, we treated uh as
auto-complete models which help you to
assist in finishing the specific context
uh which you are working with. So, in
terms of code, imagine you are like
typing some function, it gathers the
local context, for example, the previous
information which is already in the
file, the future information um
and that's already enough for it to just
complete a small piece in the middle uh
for the function which you work. But
again like the scope is very small, it's
super local, and the key feature for
co-pilot models is that they should be
like instant, super fast such that
uh you know, you can press a tab and it
work like an auto-complete. And
actually, when when we were talking in
the early stages of our podcast when we
were talking with people like uh Tabnine
in the early days when we they were
saying some super interesting things
about how the speed at which uh an
auto-complete basically a co-pilot like
you say, the speed at which that
delivered an answer
massively like talking split seconds
massively changed the user the developer
experience with those whether people
would want to use them or not. And
typically, it's because they provide
small responses. They're short responses
that I as an individual know what I
should expect and know what I I can
actually type it myself most likely cuz
I'm not asking it to do something huge.
It's just a single line or something
that is
very often based on the very local
context of the of the method, etc. Yeah,
I think like in the early days, these
co-pilot models, the the requirement for
it to be super fast was extremely
important because they were just not
able to deliver complex stuff and that's
why people were very picky and serious
about the speed of it. Now, there's a
relaxation of this requirement and I
think people are ready to wait more if
this uh co-pilot models could, you know,
achieve like or
really execute a very complex scenario.
I can think of a actual scenario where
you are defining, let's say, a class and
you're writing a docstring for a class.
Um so, the docstring can be quite
complex, right? It can include a lot of
details about like your intentions, how
this class will look like, what it will
do. And I think now that agents are so
sorry, not agents like assistants,
co-pilots are so smart, people are okay
to wait couple of more seconds
um and the tolerance to wait uh is now
like growing. That that like literally
literally fine because they their
capabilities just growing up. Uh that's
our um
uh co-pilots. Again like their core
feature, usually, they are small, they
are instant in response. The next
generation of the models is AI
assistants
uh and this is the first moment I think
where the agentic capabilities are
already uh presented.
Uh maybe not in the full picture, but
still like a lot of them already there.
So, their purpose is to assist with user
tasks and this is the first moment where
user task can be actually anything. It
can be code generation, but it can be
planning, it can be searching for and
doing them doing the market research.
Like the purpose of the assistant can be
different. The capabilities the core
capabilities for uh this assistant is to
respond to the user requests. So, like
as assistant word means like uh
it waits for your for your response, it
outputs you uh it you know, like result
of execution and it further waits for
for another clar- clarifications or
another commands. So, it um it iterates
with it interacts with you in a chat
chat way.
Uh it doesn't generate like a long plan,
it doesn't focus on the long horizon
tasks. It's focused specifically on what
to do what you want to do right now. And
I think like the core another important
uh detail is that uh user makes the
decisions. So, user is always in the
loop uh and that's what is the
differentiator factor for
between the agent and the system. And
nowadays, I think like yes, definitely
like AI agents are growing and becoming
massively adopted, but still in
practice, people are mixing
the term AI agent with AI assistant. And
if you're using a cursor with a top
interactive tab open on the right, then
you're using using AI assistant because
you're always there to chat with the
model and fix it. And even if you're
using cloud code, which is technically
AI agent, you're still very likely use
it as a system because you're typing
commands, you validate the results, and
if you're unhappy, then you ask it to
redo something. So, so would you say
they are
they have that agentic capability, but
typically the way we use them is as an
assistant.
So, the the difference between a the
difference between an agent or an
assistant
is almost the way we use it versus
capabilities. Maybe it's different
versions or not versions, but different
implementations and offerings will be
better at certain things versus other,
whether it's
the longer term more autonomous tasks
versus the other, but it's typically
how we interact. Correct. So, I think
if we want to highlight the border, then
like assistants they're again like
interacting with the user, waiting for
the response. And
the user makes the decisions. But for AI
agents, usually they can be treated as
proactive
tasks, like assistants which can do like
long horizon, very challenging,
multi-step complex tasks,
sometimes not requiring human in the
loop. That's the definition of the AI
agent, at least in this taxonomy which
we introduced of four core entities. AI
agent is like on the top because AI
agent can technically
do not require human to be there to
achieve the task. And let's go into
agency a little bit deeper in terms of
the way we use them. Um you mentioned
cursor, you mentioned code code. Very
different usage patterns in terms of one
uses a terminal UI, one uses a more
classical IDE.
If we look at others, in fact, quite a
few have almost favored either IDE or
terminal, but there are a surprising
number that favor terminal these days.
Is there a best way to use an agent? Is
there a way that is you know, easier for
us to give an agent information or
context? Or is it really up to the user
depending on how the user prefers to
interact with that agent?
>> Yes, I think
the interactivity is the differentiator
factor. Like when you're using an IDE
with a extension like a cursor
being like visible to you, then you are
like agreeing to to the scenario where
you are in the loop. You're always
checking what happens, and you're just
doing this interactively. So, UI
elements like simplify
and
you know, like accelerate the onboarding
for you as a developer. It doesn't
replace you as a developer. It's just
like here on the side exist to help you
with achieving like specific tasks like
executing helping you to write a
specific code file or specific unit test
and so on. And be very helpful in the
sense that there is a UI. You don't need
to know any commands because there are
buttons, and
it's just like a box for you to type the
text and execute. So,
I think like the cool
part of the cursor or WinServe is that
they are
giving you this IDE
with a
with lots of UI elements to help you
onboard to using these tools more like
proactively and in your everyday use
case. While for AI agents like with
terminal, by definition, like you don't
need like
buttons, right? Like complex things
complex things can be done just with the
combination of the of the of the of the
keys
or the commands. So, terminal is like
for more advanced users
for those who are ready to accelerate
even further because they don't need to
have have a visualization. They are okay
just like living in the terminal and
manipulating all the commands in the
terminal. Because if you're at some
point advanced the Vim or Nana or
whatever editor
or a Git, you actually don't need UIs,
right? You can just do and achieve very
hard scenarios with terminal directly,
and it saves you time. But again like
it's just like a bit harder because it's
less interactive because it's easier to
to lose what happens.
And I think the
the amount of the generated information
sometimes maybe overwhelming, so it's
hard to navigate for the terminal just
because there's so many things that are
happening, and it requires some skill to
learn how to use it properly. Yeah,
absolutely. And I think things like
cursor, for example, where you see the
the the changes and you can flip from
file to file very very easily. You
obviously miss that from the from the
terminal point of view. But I don't know
what it is about, you know, just being
on a terminal that actually just makes
me feel faster, more productive at the
terminal.
And of course, when you're at the
terminal, you get the power of the
terminal, right? It's it's it tell us a
little bit about how you can effectively
use the terminal beyond just code code.
Yeah, that's true. And another super
advantage of the terminal solution is
that like
it gives you a better way to run your
agent in the background, right? Like you
can run the cloud code code X terminal
CLI in the non-interactive mode
just for a CLI giving a prompt what you
want to, you know, what you want from
this agent to to do, and it will spawn a
background process and fully on its own
start executing
this complex request which you asked it.
But I think nowadays actually like any
AI system tools like such as cursor,
they are also moving in this direction,
and they're adding more and more
capabilities. For example,
a couple of months ago cursor couldn't
have access to a terminal. So, you if
you run something, you need to you
needed to copy and paste directly in the
in the text box
of the of the cursor
the error message, for example. But now
it actually has access to a terminal, so
it has access to the information which
you are in the terminal like
using. So, that's one thing. And now
there's that cursor also launched their
own agent, which can be also
non-interactive or CLI. So, they are
covering this space as well.
You know, they want to get both sides
and both people like who are who want to
interact who want to have more
interactivity and who who want who are
okay to
work just with CLI. It's fairly how
I think we're fairly familiar you and I
with trying out a bunch of these, and I
think everything that we've mentioned so
far I've definitely played with, I'm
sure you have. And there's obviously a
bunch of others, Gemini CLI. I think you
actually maybe mentioned Gemini. Code X
is another. Where would you say like for
for those listening who are kind of like
on the you know, trying to trying to
follow this 101 working out well, where
do I actually start? Where would you say
is like a good place to start? Is there
is there one good place or is it really
depending on where where a user is most
consistently, you know, doing those
tasks? Should they try and find an agent
in that environment? What would you
recommend? I think it depends on the
level of experience and maybe on the
role of the person in the company if
we're talking about some some technical
people because definitely there are no
code solutions, right? Like Lovable, for
example, that
that provides your
live coding platform for developing
backends and frontends instantly without
any knowledge of the code. So, it
requires you zero knowledge. It just
requires you to be there to validate and
approve the the the content generated by
the AI
assistant or whatever.
And the more the the closer you are to
the code
and the more scale you need,
then the more advanced tools you need to
use,
which require potentially a lot of
manual resolution
of the problems. So, for example, if you
are like a software engineer and you're
writing and your your goal is to develop
a lot of software tasks and a lot of
manipulations with the code, then you're
okay to start with first of all a
copilot just to see if your if the
copilot models are helping you to at
least accelerate your productivity
as a as a developer. So, does it help
you to write a better faster code? If
you're happy with the copilot, then
you're going to the next extension and
go with a cursor IDE when you're
starting using these complex assistants
as your companions helping you achieve
the task. And now the scope of autonomy
and what assistants can do grows. So,
you can delegate it to change not just a
function, but entire files. And once
you're okay with that, then you can can
move to the top of this hierarchy and
start using cloud code and cursor or
Gemini CLI
directly in the terminal because now you
know the strong sides of these. Now you
know what you can delegate it, and
probably you're already like familiar
with a core capabilities and familiar
with how these
tools are working. So, you can delegate
even more scope in a fully autonomous
pipeline or setup. So, I think the
the reasoning should be like that.
Start with something super simple which
doesn't require any knowledge of code,
and if you already have a knowledge,
then progress further
and
go into more and more advanced
tools. I think it's a really really good
advice in terms of it's not just
actually about Well, there's two things
I think here. One one is that there's a
trust implication, and it's important to
be in control like when we start
learning how to drive, we don't jump
into a Ferrari and try and try and try
and drive that Ferrari. It's about do
you know taking small steps.
Once we're comfortable with it, once we
trust ourselves as well as the tools
that we have, we go on to the next step.
And and this growth in autonomy is is
all about that growth in trust. I I
absolutely love that. And I and I like
the the focus there as well in terms of
you know, sticking to where you're most
familiar in that sense of if you're if
you're familiar with an IDE, well, maybe
let's let's start you know, what when
you go from there maybe GitHub Copilot
or something like that in the IDE is the
best place. And then maybe cursor if you
want to stay with IDE. If you love
terminals, maybe dip into something else
from from from that. Really really like
that advice. Some some of our listeners
may have heard of subagents before. What
what's the difference between an agent
and a subagent? Some like subagents is
basically an instance
uh like another instance of an agent
just spawned and controlled by the main
agent. And you usually use that when
your task is so complex that one agent
is not enough to tackle it. And when
there are different options or different
paths that can be explored. Uh so I
think like yeah two two scenarios where
the the problem is so complex that it
needs to be split into smaller parts or
when you need to make a search to like
just explore the space and
to just one of one of the options. So
like yeah these two scenarios. But
basically subagent is just like another
instance of uh of a main agent which is
asked to solve a specific problem.
So uh you can think of it as a master
slave architecture. Uh right like if you
are for example interacting with a
master agent with with the one which is
you have access in your terminal.
Uh and you ask it to develop a um a
service that has a front end and a back
end, then it's a great candidate for
splitting uh and spawning a subagents.
One subagent will be working on the back
end, another agent will be working on
the front end.
Um and they will be doing their like
pieces independently. And then at some
point they will go back to the master
uh agent to communicate back the result.
And the master will decide are they okay
or like is the result is fine? Does it
satisfy the overall goal? And if not,
then it will circle back the the
information to them and give a feedback.
And they like continue iterating or
refining uh based on the feedback which
they received to improve this back end
and front end. That's a
uh example of how to use subagents for
coding assistance, for tasks beyond
coding where you need like exploration.
Uh subagents might be just like a
parallel instances of the same agent
which are just exploring the problem
from different angles. For example, you
want to search
um
for some information like to answer some
specific question. And then you can make
a search with one type of query in the
Google, you can make a search over the
articles in the Wikipedia, you can do a
search over the information available in
your I don't know like local database.
And for all that scenarios, they all
about the search of the information in
different sources, but they are done by
just like a different agents.
Technically speaking,
uh in in some future there won't be need
uh in subagents because the master agent
will be so smart and will be knowing how
to
um how to resolve any challenging
problem uh on its own. So it won't it
won't you know, lose and won't forget
about the context. It will know how to
navigate in this complex structure on
its own. And technically it won't need
to have spawning subagents. Um but
another reason for another motivation
for the subagents is just like speed.
All we we know that agents are super
slow. If you try to paralyze them and
subagents is one way of doing this, you
just get the result faster. You just get
like 10 implementations of the same
thing and maybe one or two of them are
good and working and doing what you were
expecting. So it's just like um like you
know, like latency
um and throughput
uh versus idling time.
Um
yeah. I think like the time that you
mentioned there and the parallelization
as well as the context are both really
good reasons to use them. Um in terms of
in terms of the cons the the the the the
negatives that that they can that they
provide, is it just is is it like
burning tokens more or anything anything
that we need to be cautious of? Yeah, I
mean like for sure like costs will grow
uh linearly, right? Like with more
agents you will cost like spend more. Um
And sometimes there might be a situation
where you again like spawn the these all
agents, but they actually didn't
converge to anything. Um
And another disadvantage is that there
are different ways how to spawn how to
launch the subagents. One is the your
main agent can launch
subagents on its own because like Claude
Code actually now gives this capability.
You can ask explicitly saying explicitly
in the prompt, use parallel agents to
analyze this complex document, right? So
you can explicitly state it in the
prompt and it will on its own spawn like
multiple versions of the agents. But the
thing is is that you can
you might want to have specialized some
subagents, right? So instead of like
general search subagents, you want to
have subagents focused on a specific
access or a specific angle of a problem.
And here you need like to have extra
customization. You need to work you need
to uh carefully design instructions for
uh for that subagent in order to get
best you know, get get great result. So
the downside that you know, like
speaking of downsides, the time for
designing the subagents. It's also like
uh an art and you need to make an
effort. If you don't do it, then
probably um main agent will do it on its
own. But the quality of the subagents
might be different because it might just
like miss uh some
some some important bits uh in in in the
instruction to the subagent.
>> Yeah. And and in terms of the agents
like other than being able to customize
an agent and be able to a subagent
rather. And and be able to say how I
want you to use this subagent when
you're when you're doing these types of
things
uh or allow it to choose the the the
appropriate kind of subagent to do those
tasks. I presume the main agent is the
is pretty much entirely the the the
communicator across subagents. There's
no human interaction between
uh that that that bypasses the main
agent. Yeah, I mean like it depends on
the design of your system and I think in
Claude Code it's very hard to control
it. Like usually the subagents are
launched on the background. So you don't
actually have access directly to see
what they are doing. You only can see it
in the logs. So if you open the
um Claude uh JSONL file to see what were
the commands, you will see that agents
were doing something on the background,
but you won't necessarily see it in your
terminal.
Uh you won't necessarily see the the
thinking process, the the path, the
planning for each of the subagents. So
yeah like again and maybe another like I
don't know disadvantage or even
advantage of this is that like you trust
it even more. So you need to believe in
in the fact that it will come up with
something uh meaningful even more if you
are entering the world of subagents.
Cool. You mentioned context management
which I think is actually a really
important part of subagents. Well, first
of all we should talk about the problems
of you know, context within agents and
when they compact why they compact
context and and how perhaps subagents
can alleviate at least some of that by
running in their in their own little
domains. Talk us through a little bit
about the the need and the problems of
context or over context for an agent.
>> Yeah, so um
behind the scenes We're going to jump
into the second half of our
conversation. But first, a quick
shout-out to AI Native DevCon. Two days
of hands-on sessions, deep dives, and
honest conversations about what it means
to build AI native software. November
18th and 19th in New York or join
virtually from anywhere. Tickets and
details at ainativedev.io/devcon.
See you there. Behind the scenes of all
the agents there are LLMs, right? Like
large language models and they are
trained with some fixed uh or maximum uh
context length. And this context length,
one of the main limitation I'll talk
about the other one.
Uh but like it usually has some like max
max size. Like 256k tokens or 1 million
tokens. So so there is a limit of how
much information can be used in the
context to the
uh to your LLM. And when we like
starting talking about agents, agent is
actually a wrapper around your LLM which
has which constantly adds something
appends something new to the context.
Right? So imagine you are starting uh
your session and asking Claude Code to
develop something,
uh it creates like you I don't know like
a bunch of files and all of this
information goes into the context. So it
already occupies some thousands of the
tokens in the context window.
And every time Claude Code tries to fix
the bug,
uh it actually also like uh adds appends
this information to the context window.
So all these trace logs, trace backs,
all this goes into the context. And it's
crazy how fast you can you know, like
reach the limit of the context memory.
Um
And uh that's
one you know, like place where subagents
can help because different instances
uh of the like different sub agents will
have their own context window
and that's that's how you like you know
increase the amount of the available
context because every every single sub
agent will maintain its own
context window
just
pre-filled with the information it
gathered from the main agent about the
instruction about the task which it
needed to accomplish but the rest of the
the rest of the context won't be
affected it's Which I think when you
talked about research so a sub agent
that does an amount of research on a
topic if it did a ton of research and
actually only 10% of that was valid the
90% wouldn't actually go back to the
main
to to to the main agent it actually only
report that 10% which it thinks is most
valid and then the agent the main agent
can go right I've got exactly the
information I need and my context window
isn't isn't overwhelmed with nonsense
>> Thanks for clarifying and and making it
like clearly understandable so yeah like
out of this thousands of tokens which
sub agent could generate only a small
bit of it like super super like small
part the the result will go into the
memory of the main agent to proceed with
the main task
and the rest of the memory will be
cleared yeah like the capacity the the
limit of the memory goes away pretty
quickly that's why we need to have some
tools for compressing and
they are implemented like compression
tools are implemented
in most of the
modern agents but that's actually like a
pretty challenging task because it's not
always obvious what information is no
more no longer useful and what is
actually still valid because like you
could
put in the memory the information about
like
initial state of the file at some point
in the beginning of your session but
then during your
interaction you were
like completely like talking and asking
the agent to solve a different problem
and then refer back to this information
which you put in in the beginning
and it could be already outdated because
of some other reasons so agent need to
know why this happened and it needs to
like spend extra tokens to understand it
okay my context is actually become
outdated I need to clear it it's
it's you know like safe to clean it
and remove the information so it does
some extra work for making this
compression so compression is a
a separate challenging task I would say
And that problem could happen again and
again and again every single time you
get your context window high enough that
it has to really redo that compression
correct
let's talk a little bit about agents and
what they're good at and what they're
not good at cuz I think we've talked a
lot about you know
how they do some of their some of their
things but
as users as let's maybe focus on
developers since this is a developer
podcast let's get let's say you know
what what what I what should I expect an
agent to be
really good at most of the time and
actually not be surprised if it if it
struggles with other tasks Very very
good question
if you can like explain in a very
thorough details the problem which you
are trying to solve so if we are talking
about a coding problem if you write a
very careful specification capturing all
the necessary aspects of your
of your product or your decisions all
the requirements there you can expect
that it will come up with a prototype
that will be at least very close to what
you want so I I mean like that's already
like a surprising right like we are in
the era where we can just populate in
plain language a huge document
describing how something complex should
work
and agent will come up with a roughly
working solution on its own so this is
where we are in terms of what agents can
do there there are lots of caveats to
that is that like usually it won't be
exactly what you want and you will need
to anyway like manual intervention and
fixes to validate that like
fix it and correct where it made some
wrong decisions
so human in the loop still essential
but again it's not a bug it's a feature
because our requirements are always
loose and we are under specifying stuff
and since we under specified
the LLM has a choice to decide on its
own if the content is under specified
how to proceed with it if you didn't say
in your specification which database to
use like post person or it's up to
the LLM to come up with what it thinks
but it's not a problem of an LLM it's
just because you under specified right
so
I would say like to sum to sum to sum up
if you give like a very clean
instruction a very detailed information
about how you see your solution should
work
and what things it should include then
it's already good enough at instruction
following to develop you a prototype
which matches your expectations both in
back end and front end I would say
There might be some
again like limitations of the solution
which it will come up with but that can
be because you were under specified in
the spec or because the task was I don't
know it sometimes it can come up with
non-efficient like unefficient solution
which which it won't be scalable and you
will anyway need to refactor it but
usually it comes also because of your
loose specification so yeah like
for sure like in one shot in few shot
you can come up with a working game
which works in your browser you can come
up with a
server which can be hosted locally and
sometimes I think you can even go beyond
that and
do even a
you know a deployment also fully
autonomously that's what at least
lovable offers right they like
fully maintain the life cycle of the
development of a front end and back end
and serving this for you and you don't
need to you don't need to make any
decisions about this so agents are that
powerful Yeah absolutely
and but let's now talk about
mentioning deployment let me think about
something that we can that we are happy
to push to production something that we
as professional developers now want to
want to
want to use and
build with in fact why don't we why
don't we think first about the actual
development environment that we that we
as professional developers need to use
there's certain things like you know
security issues for example if I'm if I
want to use cloud code locally
you know it's going to have full access
to my system if I want to run things
locally okay what's happening now what
where do I need to kind of first of all
think from a from a professional point
of view of locking down my system a
little bit more Yeah absolutely so like
basically if you're
working on your like local version of
the repo and you're giving a full access
to the cloud code to work on it at some
point it can do rm minus rf
accidentally and if you do don't do a
checkpoint then you're in trouble
and there are lots of stories on the
Reddit where cloud code like went that
crazy and did that
and in order to you know like
accelerate the professional development
experience there are like
different approaches how to do that
one which you can do on your own you can
spawn cloud codes always in the isolated
environments so you can
like create a separate docker container
which will have a replica of your repo
and you will you know send the commands
to this docker container and
agent will in this isolated environment
will be working on a replica and
actually that's one branch of a
solving these issues with the
permissions and with the scare of being
of being scared to remove something so
isolated environments that's that's
where you can
solve you know
some of the issues another type of
problem with the security for example
related to the API keys for example what
if you are asking your agent to write
another agent right like for example you
are a company which develop develops
like agents for some reason and to test
this agent
it might need to have access to the API
token
right and if you provide this API token
then it can go crazy there because it
can start doing infinite tasks basically
burning your budget
and um
this this is
for these types of the you know like
issues that's much more hard like much
harder to come up with something some
some security solution
unless you cut off the internet
completely
but yeah like that's a type of the
security concern but yeah like speaking
of the main approach the sandboxing
environments that's what um
allows you to solve most of the problems
Another way of solving is a solving
these types of problems is like again
like limiting the available tools for
the agents for example agent cannot
write
or edit
files under specific directories so you
are as the user in the loop can create
these rules and this will prohibit agent
from making like dangerous actions from
very sensible
you know like libraries or directories
where there's a lot of sensitive
information and yeah like some tools for
example Gemini CLI comes with a sandbox
solution available out of the box so if
you start a Gemini session with a
sandbox from your current directory then
it will make a clone of your repo in the
isolated docker container and you can
also specify which commands or which
tools are available so you can you can
disconnect it from the internet for
example and then
it will just like start working in the
isolated environment and you don't need
to do
any manual spawning of
>> Yeah.
Yeah, that's one way to to look at this.
Yeah, very interesting.
And what about memory and memory
management? Is this is this something
that's kind of like similar
similar controls that we would have? So
basically some providers
like again like Gemini CLI also works on
the tools which help you to
have a fine-grained control over the
memory of the agent so you can make a
checkpoint, you can make a snapshots of
the context that was at some point in
the memory of the agent. Once you
snapshot it, you can finish the session,
you can close the terminal, and you can
restart it the other day and resume from
a specific context
from a specific you know point in in
time where you were developing. And
Which I think is super valuable, right?
Because with with particularly when
you're thinking about professional
development environments, you you you
want them to work in certain ways. And
and it's about it's about retaining that
information so I don't need to say again
and again and again like you know you're
speaking to a child.
Don't do this, do this, don't do this,
do this. Sometimes like you are also as
a developer you're not sure about the
solution which you want to see in the
end so you are communicating and
chatting with an agent to propose you
multiple implementations, right? And
then you snapshot each of these and at
some point in the future like you want
to decide to come back to a specific one
which you like the most and you want to
revert your context to the specific
point in time to the approach which you
like. So that's
like it just makes your environment
clean and
clean and easy to control so it's no
longer messy. You don't need to remember
where you did you commit your
changes to a specific branch such that
you never lose the information which
agent already generated or so you you
just like
you just eliminate from your brain
context some information which is
maybe not useful
because you have access to explicitly
store
snapshots of the memory. And yeah,
that's what that's that's a super cool
feature for especially professional
development developers or working with
many branches or working with many
features
at scale. I'm working within an
organization as well where there's
probably a bunch of shared knowledge.
And I guess you know perhaps there are
organizational policies
or organizational styles, ways of
working, things that you know the
platform team want you to do or don't
want you to do. Can we can we
allow this knowledge to be shared
through
through context management as well,
organizational context management? Yeah,
so I think
um
most of the tools are focusing on the
context which is local which is
available like in the local environment
and uh
for example you can you can for sure
have a Gemini MD or Claude MD or agent
MD file where you explicitly say
and refer to other
markdown files to other documentation to
such that when agents will be started
will be triggered it will have all the
information about your security
guidelines, the code guidelines and so
on. There's a
some problem with that is that
again if you overload the context with
so many instructions the agent can be
just confused and can just you know get
lost
into this
terabytes like
flow of information
plus sometimes the instructions can be
overwhelming and conflicting and it's
unclear what to do in this case.
So I would say that's a great
not just a research topic but a product
topic and many companies will try to
solve this for sure because how to
introduce the tribal knowledge of your
company and knowledge about the
security guidelines efficiently the
coding guidelines and so on efficiently
such that you could your agent could
benefit and use it all the time for your
when you're doing like coding and never
forgets about this and always respected
it.
That's an open problem. I don't think
like any of the existing
like providers or vendors of the agents
solve this explicitly but there are like
definitely like approaches for that. For
example Gemini CLI gives you access to
directly write some memories into the
into the agent's memory. I think it's
called flash memory update
and a prompt. It will attend your prompt
to the Gemini MD and refresh the Gemini
MD in the memory in the context memory
of the agent. So that's one way to
introduce
super recent information directly into
the context.
Or Claude code which introduced this
concept of skills, right? Where you have
um
bunch of
like independent things like skills
which can be dynamically fetched
in the context memory depending on
what's the situation is.
So that's that's a way like that these
are the approaches for for for the from
the vendors to tackle this complex
problem of respecting your specific
choices and decisions. And of course
Tessal
are kind of leading into this space as
well, right? In and around context
management of of of holding
organizational data a little bit as well
as various open source
kind of usage specs I guess as well as
proprietary. Tell us a little bit about
how that kind of can level up your
agents I suppose in in more professional
environment. Yeah. So this the concept
of the usage specs is that like
it's the easiest to explain it in the
in the example of third-party dependence
third-party dependencies. So imagine you
are working with a
library with some framework and it has
many dependencies.
And if you want to implement in your
library a feature related to this
dependency, right? Then you need to make
sure that the agent the code agent has a
lot of capabilities and lots of
knowledge about this dependency.
But imagine this is not a very popular
library. Imagine that's like something
which was just released recently and it
was not a part of the training data for
the Claude code or for any foundational
LLM so
LLM just doesn't know how the API of
this dependency looks like.
And the only way to solve it is either
to have a access to the source code
which is super inefficient, right?
Because it will require the agent to
clone the the repo to navigate through
thousands of the files and so on or it
can just like try to import this
dependency and try to test this the
functionality available in this repo in
the dummy script which again is also
inefficient in terms of turns, right?
Like agent will spend lots of time just
understanding how to work with this
library. So why would you do that?
No reasons. You want to be efficient,
right? You can use usage specs. Usage
specs is a compressed
representation of the API of this
library which can be consumed by your
agent from the Tessal registry or from
your private registry because Tessal is
also working on the having registries
for for for companies. And if you
consume this you know usage specs, it's
just like a bunch of the documents which
show how the
API is designed for this specific
package, then agent has direct access to
the very clear
knowledge of how to how to work with
with this specific library. It doesn't
need to scan thousands of files. It has
everything stored in a very nicely
formatted and easily accessible
for you like directly here. So it's very
token efficient
turns efficient and working because like
we made a big effort to make that these
usage specs valuable and containing lots
of information. So
usage specs not only show the API
methods and the definitions but also how
to use them. What are the best
scenarios? What are the underlying
implications of using this specific
API? So that's
one you know way how to look into the
usage specs
as a way to
learn
to
to give you know to give your agent a
knowledge about some library which was
never part of the pre-training data or
which is not popular or which is a
private, right? Which was
you know like agent just doesn't know
about this. Yeah, awesome. Let's wrap
this section up by talking about evals
cuz I think when we talk about
professional development, we need to
know we need to be able to test. We need
to be able to say okay these agents are
best because
they can do these particular things
really well. I will use these other
agents because they can do these other
things particularly well maybe reviews
or tests or whatever. How do we
what's a good way to be able to eval an
agent's capability as let's say code
generation? So it's a huge topic because
like there are so many ways to This is a
podcast episode by itself but let's try
to cover it in the in 5 minutes.
So yeah, eval is just like super complex
topic on its own like it's a very
complex like how to eval LLMs in general
like because they can do literally so
many things but how do you eval this?
And it becomes more and more challenging
even if you try to limit the scope just
to code generation because apparently
code generation is also like a super
complex
you know task and uh
evaluating the capabilities of the agent
specifically in this domain is also
challenging. So, I would say the most
common way to do this now in the
community and in the research
environment and in academia is to use
like
popular benchmarks such as SWE-bench,
specifically a verified variant of it,
which was popularized by OpenAI. So, the
way these evals are working
in a sense in some sense they are
reflecting their real development
process. They are taking your repository
in the state before some feature was
implemented.
Then it asks you to implement the
specific feature, right? It gives you a
repo before the feature was there. It
gives you requirements about what how
the feature should look like. It gives
you some maybe information about the API
and how
how it is intended to be implemented.
Then you launch your agent, your coding
assistant, which that does the work to
implement the missing files, the
missing feature. And once it generated
this patch, right? Like this update,
it is evaluated against a commit which
has real tests, which has real unit
tests approved by the human, so which we
can treat as a ground truth. And if your
agent proposed patch passes this test,
then you can think of it as a success
and ooh, your agent implemented
everything properly. So, it works as
expected.
So,
that's
the most common way how to how to test
it. Of course, it's very hard to design
such benchmark, right? Like because
in reality you can't just go to GitHub
and clone any package, pick a PR and use
this
PR
as a as a, you know, like a source for
your
evaluation because many PRs are lacking
of documentation. They don't declare any
any information about like design
choices and so on. So, you need to
filter the data very aggressively to
just include
those data points where your agent has
theoretically like a chance to solve
this problem, right? Like because
your your PR description, the issue
description should be enough and should
contain enough information for the agent
to solve the problem.
And if it misses the definitions of the
API, if it misses some assumptions that
agent just like theoretically doesn't
have chances to come up with
uh, with the right solution. So,
SWE-bench alike evaluations is the most
common approach, but
again, like it's very limited. If you
look into into the SWE-bench pro
tasks, then they are usually touching
only one file. Rarely they touch two
files. And again, like that's not real
software development experience, right?
Like usually when you ship a feature,
you're shipping like
five or six files. You're making changes
in many places
and you need to be super accurate in
imports, in unit tests and so on. So,
the real PRs are much more challenging
than what we have in
SWE-bench pro. So, that's why we need
like
a new benchmark.
It can be It can be of the same format,
but it needs to be a next level
requiring the agent to make changes not
in one file, but in a collection of
files. So, more of a guideline or a
a signal versus something that's more
complete in terms of will will
absolutely relate to your exact
experience. Exactly. And also this type
of eval, I think it focuses mainly on
the software engineering backend tasks,
but what if we go to the
agents which are
which can produce
UI, right? Like how do you evaluate the
UI? Or what if you are developing an
agent which interacts with a database
and can change the state of the
database, right? Like it's a different
type of eval and it's it's a different
type of a complexity and community is
now working on a specific like dedicated
benchmarks for assessing these
capabilities as well. Like if your agent
generated a UI, how you evaluate that it
is like matching the
the request in the in the user prompt.
How like how can we trust that what it
came up with actually matches the
expectations? Yeah. Yeah, so that's like
a pick of an iceberg.
Absolutely. Let's Let's wrap up with I
guess what's next for agents or what
what what are the what are the things
that you're most looking forward to in
whatever this next generation of agents
AI agents looks like. One of my
expectation is that like agents should
at some point learn how to write a
better code
because
now nowadays the quality of the code
they produce
sometimes it's like just like a garbage.
It's like
you can feel that it's a one-time
script.
It's really not something which you will
enjoy to come back at some point like
later in the timeline and work on top of
that. A lot of the code which LLM
generates that's super garbage, messy,
not scalable. So, um,
and of course you can deal with it by
having more guidelines about how to
write the code, but still I think it's
an open challenge to improve the quality
of the generated code
in general for the agent. So, that's my
one expectation. Second is of course
like improving the
UI capabilities. So, like most of the
existing agents they are struggling
with creating a really nice UIs
following your specific instructions.
So, I expect the core models to get
improvement over there.
And
I think
I would love to see like we talked a
little bit about the SWE-bench eval. So,
I want to see
a new version of the a more challenging
version of SWE-bench and people are
working on that. For example, SWE-pro.
That's a much more complex and
challenging variant of the SWE-bench
where agent is just like
facing harder tasks, which again like
require it to make changes in multiple
files and accuracy falls dramatically,
which makes all the claims that agents
can execute long horizon tasks kind of
not valid. So, um,
really having very complex PRs, having
making agents solving really complex
tasks which require changes in multiple
files, this is the way to
make it able to solve long horizon
tasks.
So, I'm expecting
to again like have more
more of an input from the academia, from
the people and investment in the better
benchmarks about how how can we trust,
how can we make sure that it is able to
generate complex code,
but also like improving the of course
definitely the the accuracy on these
benchmarks.
And that's a great way to wrap up with a
tell me I'm a research engineer without
telling me I'm a without saying I'm a
research engineer without talking about
evals.
So,
Max, this has been this has been
extremely interesting and thorough.
Really, really appreciate all your
knowledge and experience here in
chatting about agents. I'd love to kind
of hear what our audience thinks in
terms of more sessions like this, more
of the kind of the 101, let's go let's
go deeper into certain agents and other
AI
technologies. We can absolutely do that.
So, let us know. Max, massive thank you.
Thank you for joining us and thank you
for sharing. Yeah, thank you very much
for having me and yeah, we'll be happy
to come back and talk more about
>> Absolutely, absolutely. This is one of
20 in a series that we're doing now,
Max. That's fun. Amazing. Thanks very
much, everyone. Really appreciate you
joining and tune in for the next
episode.